<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE lingPaper PUBLIC "-//XMLmind//DTD XLingPap//EN"
"XLingPap.dtd">
<lingPaper
automaticallywrapinterlinears="yes"
version="2.20.0"
><frontMatter
><title
><object
type="tFlextrans"
></object
> User Documentation</title
><author
>Ronald M. Lockwood</author
><emailAddress
>flextrans.help@gmail.com</emailAddress
><date
>1 November 2016</date
><version
>1.3.7 (Sense Linker 2.1)</version
><contents
></contents
><abstract
><p
>This paper describes how to use the <object
type="tFlextrans"
></object
> machine translation system. It is a supplement to my master's thesis which goes into more detail on the background and documents a test case. Please see <link
href="https://digital.lib.washington.edu/researchworks/handle/1773/33999"
>A Linguist-Friendly Machine Translation System for Low-Resource Languages</link
>.</p
></abstract
></frontMatter
><!--<section1
id="s0"
><secTitle
>Introduction</secTitle
><p
>Main sections to read in the thesis to get oriented.</p
>
</section1
><section1
id="s1"
><secTitle
>FLExTrans Modules</secTitle
><p
></p
></section1
>
--><section1
id="sLinker"
><secTitle
>The <object
type="tSenseLinker"
></object
></secTitle
><p
>The <object
type="tSenseLinker"
></object
> is a tool for linking source senses to target senses. The tool looks through the text specified in the configuration file and lists every sense that was analyzed in that text in order. Here's sample screen shot of the <object
type="tSenseLinker"
></object
>:</p
><example
num="xLinkerToolShot"
><chart
><img
XeLaTeXSpecial="scaled='600'"
cssSpecial=" height:60%"
src="Images/SenseLinkerCapture.png"
></img
></chart
></example
><p
>Here's a key to the color coding:</p
><table
border="1"
><tr
><th
>Color</th
><th
></th
></tr
><tr
><td
>White</td
><td
>Source sense has been linked to a target sense.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
>Red</td
><td
>Source sense has not been linked to a target sense.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
>Light Blue</td
><td
>A target sense has been suggested for this source sense through a partial match of the glosses.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
>Blue</td
><td
>A target sense has been suggested for this source sense through an exact match of the glosses.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
>Green</td
><td
>The target sense has been set or changed for this source sense.</td
></tr
><tr
><td
>Red Text</td
><td
>There is a mismatch of grammatical category even though the glosses match.</td
></tr
></table
><p
>For suggested sense links (colored in blue), if you want to link them, simply check the check box in the Link It column. To link a source sense with a target sense where there is no suggestion or to change an existing link, you need to do two things. First, select the target sense that you want to link to in the drop down list of senses () then go to the Target Head Word column for the source sense in question and double-click there. The target sense information should appear with a green background color.</p
><p
>If you only want to see the senses that need to be linked, check the box that says Show Only Unlinked.</p
></section1
><section1
id="sRuleTester"
><secTitle
>The <object
type="tLiveRuleTester"
></object
></secTitle
><p
>The <object
type="tLiveRuleTester"
></object
> is a tool that allows you to test source words or sentences live against transfer rules. This tool is especially helpful for finding out why transfer rules are doing what you expect them to do. You can zero in on the problem by selecting just one source word and applying the pertinent transfer rule. In this way you don't have to run the whole system against the whole text file and all transfer rules. Here's sample screen shot of the <object
type="tLiveRuleTester"
></object
>:</p
><example
num="xTesterImage"
><chart
><img
XeLaTeXSpecial="scaled='400'"
cssSpecial=" height:40%"
src="Images/LiveRuleTester.png"
></img
></chart
></example
><section2
id="sTesterQuickGuide"
><secTitle
>Quick Guide</secTitle
><p
>Here's a quick guide on using the tool.</p
><ol
><li
>First you want to choose something from your source text that you want to test. When you first run the tool, the words of the first sentence are shown both in the drop down list at the top and in the peach colored area. You can check one or more words and when you do the <genericRef
gref="gDataStream"
>data stream format</genericRef
> of the words is shown in the blue colored area. You can quickly select a whole sentence, by clicking on the Select Sentences tab and clicking the check box for the sentence you want.</li
><li
>Next select which rule or rules you want to run against the words you selected. Check the check boxes in the purple area as appropriate. Check them all with the Select All button. Uncheck them all with the Refresh button. Move a rule up or down by clicking on it and clicking the up or down arrow buttons.</li
><li
>Now you are ready to test. Click the Test button and the selected works will get processed. The results will show in <genericRef
gref="gDataStream"
>data stream format</genericRef
> in the green colored area.</li
><li
>Check the yellow Information box. It will show which words were matched for the rules that were executed.</li
></ol
></section2
><section2
id="sTesterOther"
><secTitle
>Other Parts of the Tool</secTitle
><p
>By default the transfer rules file, the bilingual lexicon file and the source text are loaded according to the configuration file. The transfer fules file and the bilingual lexicon file can be changed if desired by clicking the corresponding Browse buttons.</p
><p
>In this version of the tool, you can't change the Source Text Name. You will have to edit the configuration file, change the SourceTextName value and re-run the tool.</p
><p
>You may have noticed that there is a Manual Entry tab for the source text words. You can enter words (technically senses) directly in <genericRef
gref="gDataStream"
>data stream format</genericRef
>. This might be useful if you want to test a sense that isn't in your text.</p
><p
>The Interchunk and Postchunk tabs for the rules list are not currently available in this version. They are for use in testing the rules that are used in the advanced <object
type="tTool"
>Apertium</object
> transfer engine.</p
><p
>You can't edit the transfer rules in the <object
type="tLiveRuleTester"
></object
> and even the change of the order of the rules in the tool does not get saved. Make your changes in a separate editor to reload the transfer rules after you have changed them, click on the Refresh button.</p
><p
>You need to have the <object
type="tTool"
>Apertium</object
> virtual machine running in order for the <object
type="tLiveRuleTester"
></object
> to work.</p
></section2
></section1
><!--<section1
id="s3"
><secTitle
>Live Rule Tester Tool</secTitle
><p
></p
></section1
><section1
id="s4"
><secTitle
>Editing Transfer Rules with <object
type="tXMLmindXMLEditor"
></object
></secTitle
><p
></p
></section1
><section1
id="s5"
><secTitle
>Configuration File</secTitle
><p
></p
></section1
><section1
id="s"
><secTitle
>Virtual Machine Processing of Transfer Rules</secTitle
><p
></p
></section1
><section1
id="s"
><secTitle
>Getting started</secTitle
><p
></p
></section1
><section1
id="s"
><secTitle
>How do I ...</secTitle
><p
></p
></section1
><section1
id="s"
><secTitle
>Working with the Sample Projects</secTitle
><p
></p
></section1
>
--><backMatter
><appendix
id="a"
><secTitle
>Appendix</secTitle
><p
></p
><section1
id="s"
><secTitle
>Data Stream Format</secTitle
><p
>The <genericTarget
id="gDataStream"
></genericTarget
><object
type="tTool"
>Apertium</object
> data stream format consists of one or more lexical units. In <object
type="tFlextrans"
></object
>, a lexical unit looks something like this:</p
><chart
><img
XeLaTeXSpecial="scaled='600'"
cssSpecial="width:60%"
src="Images/LexicalUnit.PNG"
></img
></chart
></section1
></appendix
><endnotes
></endnotes
><references
></references
></backMatter
><languages
><language
id="lVernacular"
name="vernacular"
></language
><language
id="lGloss"
name="gloss"
></language
><language
id="en"
></language
></languages
><types
><comment
>The following types are provided as pre-set examples. You may well want to create your own types that refer to one or more of these. You do that by typing in the names of the types in the types attribute of your type.</comment
><type
font-weight="bold"
id="tBold"
></type
><type
font-style="italic"
font-weight="bold"
id="tBoldItalic"
></type
><type
font-weight="bold"
id="tEmphasis"
></type
><type
after="FLExTrans"
id="tFlextrans"
types="tTool"
></type
><type
after="FLEx"
id="tFlexx"
types="tTool"
></type
><type
id="tGrammaticalGloss"
types="tSmallCaps"
></type
><type
font-style="italic"
id="tItalic"
></type
><type
after="Live Rule Tester Tool"
id="tLiveRuleTester"
types="tTool"
></type
><type
cssSpecial="text-decoration:none"
id="tNoOverline"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;no-overline&quot;"
></type
><type
font-variant="normal"
id="tNoSmallCaps"
></type
><type
cssSpecial="text-decoration:none"
id="tNoStrikethrough"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;no-line-through&quot;"
></type
><type
cssSpecial="text-decoration:none"
id="tNoUnderline"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;no-underline&quot;"
></type
><type
cssSpecial="text-decoration:overline"
id="tOverline"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;overline&quot;"
></type
><type
font-style="normal"
font-variant="normal"
font-weight="normal"
id="tRegular"
></type
><type
after="Sense Linker Tool"
id="tSenseLinker"
types="tTool"
></type
><type
font-family="Charis SIL Small Caps"
id="tSmallCaps"
></type
><type
XeLaTeXSpecial="line-through"
cssSpecial="text-decoration:line-through"
id="tStrikethrough"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;line-through&quot;"
></type
><type
XeLaTeXSpecial="subscript"
cssSpecial="vertical-align:sub;"
font-size="65%"
id="tSubscript"
xsl-foSpecial="baseline-shift='sub'"
></type
><type
XeLaTeXSpecial="superscript"
cssSpecial="vertical-align:super;"
font-size="65%"
id="tSuperscript"
xsl-foSpecial="baseline-shift='super'"
></type
><type
color="navy"
font-family="Courier New"
font-weight="bold"
id="tTool"
></type
><type
XeLaTeXSpecial="underline"
cssSpecial="text-decoration:underline"
id="tUnderline"
xsl-foSpecial="text-decoration=&quot;underline&quot;"
></type
><type
after="XMLmind XML Editor"
id="tXMLmindXMLEditor"
types="tTool"
></type
><comment
>Add your custom types here.</comment
></types
></lingPaper
>
